<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The reasoning apostate, or, Modern latitude-man consider'd, as he opposeth the authority of the King and Church occasioned by several late treatises / by John Warly ...</title>
            <author>Warly, John, d. 1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67622</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W877</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11108</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11821992</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11821992</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49594</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67622)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49594)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 555:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The reasoning apostate, or, Modern latitude-man consider'd, as he opposeth the authority of the King and Church occasioned by several late treatises / by John Warly ...</title>
                  <author>Warly, John, d. 1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 117, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T. Basset ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49594:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE Reaſoning Apoſtate: Or MODERN LATITUDE-MAN CONSIDER'D, As he oppoſeth the Authority OF THE KING and CHURCH.</head>
            <p>OCCASION'D By ſeveral late TREATISES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> John Warly <hi>B. D. late Fellow of</hi> Clare-Hall <hi>in</hi> Cambridg.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>T. Baſſet</hi> at the <hi>George</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> 1677.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:49594:2"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR</p>
            <p>7 March, 1677.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Geo. Hooper</hi> R<hi rend="sup">mo.</hi> D<hi rend="sup">no.</hi> 
               <hi>D. Gilb. Cant.</hi> Arch. à Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cris Domeſticis.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:49594:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>WHen I ſaw the Church and Religion defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>only</hi> by Reaſon, I lookt on its condition as De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable as a <hi>forlorn Hope,</hi> FOr rational Aſſertors of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, who ſcorn the <hi>Aux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iliaries</hi> of the Church, though they appear as <hi>ſtout Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> yet they are ill Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plin'd, and as <hi>Goliah,</hi> ſet up with a natural Fortitude and
<pb facs="tcp:49594:3"/>prodigious Bulk, more fit for a <hi>Spectacle</hi> than a <hi>Fight,</hi> more fit for <hi>Inquiſitive Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation</hi> than <hi>Practical Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion;</hi> And that which ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders Reaſon thus <hi>uncapable of putting</hi> an end to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes, is this, becauſe there are ſome Doctrines in obſcure places of Scripture, which are like <hi>Garriſons</hi> on ſuch a Rock which bids Defiance to Reaſon to Storm it, or Art to ſurprize it. <hi>Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> (which God alone by the Mediation of the Church)
<pb facs="tcp:49594:3"/>will moſt fully reveal and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver to Man.</p>
            <p>It is well known that ſome obſcure Texts of Scripture, as Chriſt the Author, appear as <hi>Incognito</hi> till the Church makes the diſcovery.</p>
            <p>I am not bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that our Saviour gave ſuch Commands to his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, as a Philoſopher did to his Scholars, who wrapt up his knowledg in obſcure Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods, as a dark Shop to commend the Wares. Yet 'tis certain that ſome places
<pb facs="tcp:49594:4"/>of Scripture are ſo hard to be underſtood, that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be call'd <hi>Oracles</hi> for their <hi>Obſcurity</hi> as much as <hi>Truth.</hi> Now who ſhall make diſcovery of it but thoſe to whom theſe Oracles of God are committed, and they are the Church.</p>
            <p>I need not trouble the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with the Contents of theſe Papers, but ſhall only ſay, that I have endeavor'd to give Religion as well as Reaſon its due, to rob Man of the one is <hi>unnatural Injuſtice,</hi> to
<pb facs="tcp:49594:4"/>ſteal from the other the worſt <hi>Sacriledg.</hi> This made me endeavour to aſſert the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Church, eſpecially in this Age in which it ſeems to be expoſed to contempt, and ſome factious perſons look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on it as in a helpleſs and weak condition, not able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it ſelf, much leſs to protect or aſſiſt others, turn the <hi>Divine Command</hi> into a <hi>Scoff</hi> and <hi>Jeer,</hi> whilſt in Deriſion they ſay, <hi>Go tell the Church.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <pb facs="tcp:49594:5"/>
            <head>Names of ſome Treatiſes more Obſcurely mentioned in the following Conſiderations.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>N.F.</hi> The natural Fanatick.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Milton,</hi> of Civil Power in Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Cauſes, page <hi>24.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Judgment of <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> of the intereſt of Reaſon in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, p. <hi>26.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Advocate of Conſcience-Liberty, p. <hi>42.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Author of <hi>Smyrk,</hi> p. <hi>43.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A <hi>Jeſuit</hi> againſt one of the <hi>Sorbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> p. <hi>74.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Advocate for Conſcience-Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, p. <hi>92.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49594:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Conſideration 1.</hi> Of the Defence of the Church of <hi>England</hi> by ſome Orthodox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, in a Method or Style which ſeems to ſome too familiar, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and ſevere.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough the admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Defence of the Church of <hi>England</hi> by ſome of the Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (which Name may be faſtened on Nobles, as well as Peaſants, though a late Author hath undertaken by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49594:6"/>
                  <hi>Chorah</hi>'s Model to aſſert each perſon a Prieſt; (as it was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to <hi>Luther</hi> by a great <hi>French</hi> Hiſtorian) deſerved as much Commendation as that ancient practice of drawing the Sword when Chriſtians ſtood on their guard whilſt they made confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their Faith; and that without imputation of Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Vain glory, have ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported the tottering Ark by their rational diſcourſes, and ſeem as men from <hi>Macedonia</hi> at St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Summons to aſſiſt the Church; yet ſome of theſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to take off from the eſtimation of the authority of the Church, they ſeem to me to be (as <hi>Caſſianus</hi> ſays of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49594:6"/>order of Men in the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church, <hi>Sacerdoturientes,</hi> a new kind of <hi>Gray Fryers</hi> in the reform'd Religion. Neither do other men ſeem leſs fatal to the Church who are as <hi>Mendicants,</hi> at leaſt in their language, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to win their deſigns by a cringing Supplication, <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you my Fathers,</hi> which they could not obtain by Arguments. Theſe men profeſſing a <hi>plaineſs</hi> of <hi>Speech</hi> and Integrity, ſeem as much ſuſpicious as the <hi>Gibeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites</hi> to make Leagues with <hi>clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Shoos</hi> whilſt Poverty pleads their cauſe. Neither are thoſe altogether excuſable who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute againſt their Adverſaries in a rational way without preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49594:7"/>the Authority of ſome an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers; ſeeing it is poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſhew, that the moſt valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Arguments which are made uſe of as a Battery againſt <hi>Atheiſts</hi> are not the meer products of their own inventions, but of others whoſe names are conceal'd by them; I know not for what reaſon except this is it, that they thought Authority would prejudice the humourſome Age, and that Books would be better eſteem'd as Anonymous, or a <hi>New Cabala</hi> to the reformed Religion, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſeems policy in Church as well as Srate (<hi>Arcana Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae</hi> as much as <hi>Imperii</hi>) to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal the Authors from whom they had their Intelligence or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49594:7"/>Imformation. This Method makes men ſtart at the citations of ancient Fathers, as the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples did at Chriſt's perſon wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king on the Waters, ſuppoſing them as evil Spirits to ſeduce them.</p>
               <p>But I paſs from this to the other branch of this Conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, which makes me aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed to think how ſome Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox perſons have been cavilled with for defending the Church in too ſevere and bitter Methods, and a charge laid on <hi>Prelates,</hi> as if they deſign'd the defence of the Church as St. <hi>Mallos</hi> is guarded with <hi>ſnarling Currs,</hi> and thoſe who aſſert their Authority eſteem'd as <hi>Cock Hectors,</hi> who win Battels more by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49594:8"/>Carlick than Strength, whilſt a ſtinking Breath defeats the Combatant.</p>
               <p>Theſe need not my Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (they have done it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) but ſuppoſe ſome Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions not ſo commendable; let it be conſider'd that it is as impoſſible for a man to mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize his language ſo when he diſputes with an Adverſity as ſhall not offend him, as it is for a man who fights a Duel, to keep up to all thoſe rules which he preſcrib'd to himſelf before the engagement. <hi>Polemical</hi> Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are like a <hi>Bolt</hi> or <hi>Shot</hi> which contracts Heat by flying. Laws in ſuch caſes cannot be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49594:8"/>and the Diſputant cannot be ſo accurate in his Language as <hi>Hortenſius</hi> in his Cown, as well as Oration, (ſuch a one deſerves to be call'd <hi>Smyrk</hi> or the <hi>Divine</hi> in <hi>mode</hi>) to be in a ſet accurate <hi>form</hi> without a wrinkle. He who diſputes with <hi>Suarez,</hi> muſt make uſe of his language. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphyſical Notions which are neceſſarily mix'd in Divine Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute, cannot be ſo plainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted by Scripture Phraſe, which in ſome caſes cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute the Adverſary any other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than the <hi>Idiot</hi> did <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> by giving him the <hi>Lye.</hi> To ſay all Adverſaries muſt be diſputed with by their own weapons; St. <hi>Paul</hi> warrants it,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49594:9"/>who draws an Argument from a Poet, when he might have cited the ſenſe out of the firſt Chapter of <hi>Geneſis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this perhaps may not ſeem ſo pertinent to the preſent caſe, for the age is ſufficiently weary'd out with Diſtinctions and terms of Art, which like <hi>dry Bones</hi> knit together, only make a <hi>Ske<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leton,</hi> not a man, but that which is cenſur'd is the launching out the licentious phraſe of Stage.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, this is unworthy of Divine Diſcourſe, and the Prieſt ought to ſcorn variety of humour or phancy in his language, as much as the <hi>Spaniard</hi> doth a fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtick Dreſs; his language ought
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49594:9"/>to ſtrike ſo much aw according to the Character given of <hi>Job, Though I ſmil'd</hi> (ſays he) <hi>they believ'd me not;</hi> though any thing drop which ſeems not of equal moment with the reſt of the Diſcourſe, the weight of the one overpoyſeth the levity of the other.</p>
               <p>This may be well ſuppos'd; for <hi>Gravity</hi> and <hi>Levity</hi> in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe ſeem to be as natural and as neceſſary as they are in Bodys: And as no bodys are ſo denſe or thick, but ſome ſubtile matter lurks in the Pores; ſo no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſo cloſe but it may have its airy matter intermix'd and in imbodi'd with it. The grave Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Ancient Fathers are
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49594:10"/>as a Witneſs of this. I could inſtance in ſome, if it were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</p>
               <p>To ſay all Arguments like, Arrows, to which a Plume is no leſs neceſſary than a ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Metal, whilſt one gives it flight, the other makes the wound. Such neceſſary Levity at leaſt may be pardonable, but Scurrility is a vice in <hi>Morals,</hi> much more in <hi>Religion.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever a ſharp and ſevere way of Arguing muſt not be omitted, for it is as neceſſary to the Prieſt as an <hi>Acid humour</hi> to the Stomach, without which the meat would not be digeſted: There is no new Method, <hi>Nazianzens</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is an evidence of it, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49594:10"/>Fathers ſharply check the Gentiles for their folly. Yet all this was without Scurrilous Language, altogether unlike to <hi>Luther</hi>'s railing Method, which occaſion'd ſome of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church to call him and his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples <hi>Mad Men.</hi> However he deſerv'd well of the Church (I preſume none will deny) and it may be retorted on thoſe who object it, that ſome of theirs have fixed odious Names on Proteſtants, <hi>Dogs, Infidels, Magicians,</hi> nay worſe, as a great Doctor ſigns their Baniſhments, in theſe words, <hi>Ut magos publica Authoritate arcemus, civitate pelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I might cite others to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49594:11"/>no leſs Black-mouth'd, but I forbear to do that, and ſhall only ſuggeſt this to the Readers thoughts. As the Church of <hi>England,</hi> though the firſt Reformers (if it can be reaſonably imagin'd that its <hi>firſt Reformers,</hi> gave any credit to the Objections of ſome of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church) were ſenſible that the Reformation was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun as in a ſtorm of paſſion and irreverent language, yet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owns not the conſequence of it, ſeeing it as a Tempeſt caſt them on a happy ſhore, now ſhall not all ſincere Chriſtians do as the firſt <hi>Reformers</hi> did; who when they ſaw Religion, well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, though in an unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49594:11"/>and boyſterous way (For which there is no reaſon of complaint in this caſe) would not have Religion ſuffer for it, for that would have argued as much folly as if a Prince ſhould diſown a Victory becauſe got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by raſh and imprudent means, or like caſting <hi>Joſeph</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Pit only out of ſpight to his <hi>Coat,</hi> if Religion ſuffer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not <hi>pleaſingly worded.</hi> I ſpeak not this as an Abettor of <hi>Lucians</hi> ſcoffs, or a <hi>Rabshekah</hi>'s railing, but only to ſhew how prudence makes uſe of them. To conclude with a late obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of ſome Anatomiſts, who ſay there is not known a certain uſe of the <hi>Splene,</hi> and that ſome
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49594:12"/>creatures may live without it. I determine nothing in this caſe, but only ſay I am confident there is no uſe of a Petulant Splene in Religious Debates.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:49594:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Conſideration II.</hi> Whether belief, which relies and depends on the Authority of the Catholick Church, and as it is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by the Civil Magiſtrate, may properly be ſaid to be forc't, and to proceed from an unwarrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able uſurpation of the right of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural reaſon.</head>
               <p>THe Church hath not been ſo effectually undermined by any Method as by repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its Authority under the odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous names of Tyranny, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling all obligation to belief un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable Impoſitions or force.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49594:13"/>Wherefore it is neceſſary to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine what is meant by force in its ſeveral acceptations, and then aſſert the Negative of the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</p>
               <p>Sometimes it is taken philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phically; for that <hi>Power</hi> which reſts a <hi>being</hi> beyond its natural inclination or tendency, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this account of it: the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of the <hi>Will</hi> muſt be accounted <hi>violent</hi> ſo far as it is concerned in Religion, and <hi>Grace</hi> it ſelf is not able to eſcape the imputation of force: for grace may as well be ſaid to be an <hi>enforcing</hi> influence on mans nature in his corrupted ſtate, as that power which according to philoſophy diverts the natural
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49594:13"/>courſe of the Elements in bodies, and impriſons them in one mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, otherwiſe they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat to their own firſt home. The fire and volatile parts would be always moving to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards heaven, and the ſluggiſh parts of earth fettered to their center. This is demonſtrated in another Treatiſe <hi>N. F. viz.</hi> that mens thoughts are with as much difficulty compoſed to a ſettled and true notion of God and the Soul, as the Elements are commanded to comply in the compoſition of natural Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; Therefore I ſhall wave this, and conſider it in another ſenſe, as it is more directly and boldly complain'd of, and that is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49594:14"/>it <hi>which relates to the authority of the Church and intereſt of the Magiſtrate</hi> in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, which is look'd upon by ſome as a Battery to deſtroy all Religion.</p>
               <p>This is the Force generally exclaim'd againſt by the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, which is an unreaſonable and an unjuſt imputation; for if the conſtant and univerſal Doctrine of the Church, which hath an obliging influence on Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious minds, muſt be call'd force, our Reformation and Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> muſt be eſteem'd violent, and conſequently illegal. For I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not apprehend that Separation
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49594:14"/>was juſtifiable on any better terms; but that the Doctrine of the Reform'd Church is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the Scriptures, with the conſent and evidence of Councils and Fathers. Beſides, this not only condemns holy Councils and Fathers, being u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurpers of Chriſtian Liberty by impoſing matters of Faith, but makes the whole Church lyable to Error, which was never yet aſſerted by any ſober mind. For though it may be granted that Councils and Fathers, each have been lyable to ſome errors, yet when there is a conſent of <hi>all,</hi> it is an infallible argument of Truth, <hi>vid. N. F.</hi> The Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is ſo ſenſible of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49594:15"/>this, that his Aſſertors know not how to inveſt him with Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility till they have intitled him to be the <hi>Virtual Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having conſidered Force as it relates to the Church, in the next place I cannot but take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of that, as it concerns the Magiſtrate or Civil Power. This is the Force which the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bartine moſt complains of, for that of the Church in its dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Cenſures, is lookt on but as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, like a Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon which hurts not, or Thunder diſcharg'd without a Bolt. To evade this power they alledg the plantation of the Goſpel, not by force of the Magiſtrate, but by winning per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49594:15"/>and to make this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, cite Chriſt's words (<hi>John</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 36.) <hi>If my Kingdom were of this World, then would my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants fight.</hi> This doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude againſt the authority of Kings in Eccleſiaſtical Caſes, for the deſign of that in this place, was to take off the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion which the <hi>Jews</hi> had of his coming, that his Kingdom was not Spiritual, but Temporal. This Interpretation is given by St. <hi>Auguſtin. Audite ergo Judaei &amp; gentes: audi circumciſio: Audi praeputium: audite omnia regna ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rena: non impedio dominationem ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtram in hoc mundo, regnum meum non eſt de hoc mundo Auguſt. in loc.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:49594:16"/>
               <p>To this purpoſe are many De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions from places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which I ſhall not largely conſider by ſhewing how di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorted by Faction beyond the intent of them, which I ſhall only name, and briefly diſcover the crookedneſs of the perverſe Interpretations; amongſt which none ſeems to be preſt more than that. <hi>Let every one be fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded in his own mind, Rom.</hi> 14.5. In this place the deſign of the Apoſtle is not to deliver up each man to his own private Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation or extravagant Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, as to command an attention to that which was deliver'd by him and the reſt of the Apoſtles, which is the greateſt Authority.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49594:16"/>For to ſuppoſe each man to rely on his own intrepretation, is to imagine him to contradict that which he adviſes in another place, <hi>That ye may with one mind and one mouth glorifie God, Rom.</hi> 15.6. For it ſeems to me to be a Paradox not intelligible, that men may be ſaid to be at <hi>unity,</hi> with as many diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent opinions of Chriſt (which may extend to Fundamentals) as there are Perſons. So long as their Faith is terminated in Chriſt, as <hi>Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo tertio</hi> in which they agree. By the ſame reaſon they may conclude that there is a Unity of opinion in <hi>Philiſophy</hi> concerning all Creatures, whether Animate or in Inanimate, becauſe all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in this general notion of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49594:17"/>
                  <hi>Subſtance</hi> or <hi>Animality,</hi> and that it is ſufficient to know them in Groſs, without more diſtinct knowledg of them. So that <hi>Metaphyſicks</hi> and natural <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy</hi> would be eſteem'd as uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs in Reaſon, as ſome Creeds or Decrees of Councils in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. But I paſs further, I cannot omit an Objection of a great Agent, for <hi>Libertiniſm</hi> ſuggeſted to the Parliament, in 59. ſhewing the impoſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the powers interpoſing in Matters of Religion in ſome caſes; for (<hi>ſays he</hi>) the Magiſtrate muſt be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey'd for Conſcience ſake; how therefore can a man be oblig'd to obey him, when ſome
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49594:17"/>duty is commanded which his Conſcience contradict. To this 'tis enough to ſay, that the fallacy lyes in the word <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> which in that place muſt not ſignifie each man's <hi>perſuaſion</hi> or <hi>apprehenſion</hi> of the Duty, for if it were ſo, ſome men would not be obliged to obey their Prine, and their fancies exempt them from ſubjection.</p>
               <p>Thus far have endeavour'd to aſſert the right of Princes in matters Eccleſiaſtical, but I ſhall not undertake to define par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in what their power conſiſts, or bound it by limits; 'Tis enough to my deſign, if I can but ſtop the mouths of a factious Multitude by breaking
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49594:18"/>and diverting the force of their Current, by ſhewing that theſe places of Scripture conclude nothing againſt Princes power, to be exerciſed in ſuppreſſing <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Hereſie.</hi> Neither ſhall I be ſo Dogmatically bold as ſome late <hi>Smyctimnians,</hi> who, as Magiſterially as others, out of a conſiſtory, declare their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the power of the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Magiſtrate</hi> (as if the title of our King had been diſtaſted by them, becauſe <hi>once</hi> deriv'd from <hi>Rome,</hi> Proclaims him only <hi>Churchwarden</hi> of the Church; Neither ſhall I wildly follow their Metaphor, nor criticiſe the Name with which Princes are called by them, for then
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49594:18"/>I muſt conſider the Church as it was once repreſented by the <hi>Ark,</hi> ſo by a <hi>Cheſt</hi> with three Keyes, the King to have one, the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy another, the People or <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> another: Each have their particular Suffrages; ſo when all agreed it was to be opened; which if it were ſo, it is to be fear'd it would be always ſhut. Neither ſhall I take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of another, who ordains the Laity <hi>Clergy,</hi> and the King himſelf according to him muſt be a <hi>Clergy Man,</hi> elſe he can have no right or power in the Church, But I ceaſe to go further in this extravagant Tract, and ſhall ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther propoſe theſe Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:49594:19"/>
               <p>Seeing it is certain, or at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent may be ſuppos'd that a Council and determination of the whole Church, is the moſt expedite means of ending Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies. Is it not reaſonable that the Magiſtrate ſhould preſs the uſe of them. Add to this that Councils are call'd by Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces power (as is confeſſed by all true Proteſtants) now is it not reaſonable that the Decrees of Councils in order to be put in practice, ſhould be as much the Princes care, as the Council was when it was call'd to Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain them. This conſider'd, will make the Chriſtian not to eſteem this Method of ſearching Truth, as a piece of forc'd Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49594:19"/>for it is no more force to Reaſon, than Children ſuffer when they are ſent to School. Let not any think themſelves injur'd by this Inſtance, as <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantick</hi> for the Doctrine of the Goſpel, as well as the Law, may be ſtyl'd a <hi>Pedagogy</hi> in that ſenſe.</p>
               <p>But here I may expect a check from a late and not Aſſertor of Libertiniſm, who blames <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> at leaſt pities him, as if he had an overſight for uſing this means to ſettle the Church, becauſe it occaſion'd ſeveral bloody Perſecutions. This is a weak Battery againſt the Church, and only deſerves to be confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Poet.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:49594:20"/>
               <q>
                  <l>Exitus acta probat; careat ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibus opto,</l>
                  <l>Quiſquis ab eventu facta notanda putat.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Succeſs is a very bad teſt of the prudence us'd in the means, for the one is not to be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd by the other, eſpecially by men who are not able to paſs Judgment on the ſucceſs, which is more intelligible and palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble always, than the means. Thus the Author is miſtaken, for the ſucceſs of that Council cannot be ſaid to be bad be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Divine Providence made uſe of thoſe Perſecutions for the more undoubted ſetling of Faith
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49594:20"/>ſeal'd with ſo many Martyrs blood. Let this alſo be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd, that the ſame would prevail againſt the Goſpel it ſelf, as well as Councils, and Chriſt himſelf blam'd by this Obſerver as much as <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> becauſe his coming occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd ſtrife, as he ſays, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.34. <hi>I came not to ſend Peace, but a Sword,</hi> as condemn other pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous means.</p>
               <p>Another way of aſſerting Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertiniſm, is by invalidating the examples of good Kings. <hi>Joſia, Aſa, &amp;c.</hi> who had more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with God, and ſo their Law more obligatory to the People; but ſucceeding Kings have no ſuch warrant to do the ſame.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:49594:21"/>
               <p>This Objection ſeems valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, but hath no ſtrength, for if the want of an immediate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation with God, deſtroys Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or at leaſt weakens it, what will become of other Kings under the Law, who had not ſuch a priviledg intimately to converſe with God, or at leaſt in ſo high a degree. To ſay all, It may as well be conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that the Paſtors of the Church are not oblig'd to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the practice of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, in all actions (ſome of which Miraculous, others ſuited to the exigency of the time, the one of which cannot, the other may not be imitated) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe none in theſe days can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49594:21"/>to the like Inſpiration, as deny that Princes may not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the examples of good Kings under the Law, becauſe later things cannot be ſo much Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries of the Almighty, as they were in that <hi>Oeconomy.</hi> Thus they have endeavour'd to invalidate the examples of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Kings, perſuading them that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the <hi>Moſaical Law</hi> and the practice of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedrim,</hi> or the practice of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> to oblige no more to Imitation, than the lives of <hi>Numa, Lycurgus,</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lawgivers in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> or the conſtitution of Heatheniſh Prieſts by the <hi>Roman</hi> Senate. This is true, if it is underſtood
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49594:22"/>of thoſe Rites and Laws which were purely <hi>Judaical,</hi> but other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in thoſe which were not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Typical.</p>
               <p>It is further urg'd, as the firſt and ſecond <hi>Oeconomy</hi> differ in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, and ſo do the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors in the ſeveral Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations; for (ſays he) <hi>all the</hi> Jewiſh <hi>Religion was in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Rights, Civil and Religious Acts ſo interwoven, that it was not eaſie to ſay whether the Church were more like a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, or the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth a Church.</hi> Then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes that the Magiſtrates buiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was only to compel out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward actions, but the Chriſtian Magiſtrate hath no ſuch task,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49594:22"/>Chriſtianity conſiſting in inward acts of the mind. This terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Objection may find a check from this conſideration, <hi>viz.</hi> That it is falſe when it ſays that all the influence good Kings had on the People, was only to promote outward acts, for that was not only converſant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about the Ceremonial, but In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental in promoting the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Law,</hi> which certainly reſpects the <hi>powers</hi> of the <hi>Mind</hi> as much, if not more, than the <hi>outward Act.</hi> Beſides in the ceremonial Acts of Law, and offering of Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, there was imply'd an Act of Faith, as well in other perſons as <hi>Abraham;</hi> otherwiſe their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars would have been no better
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49594:23"/>than Shambles, and their Prieſts than Slaughtermen. Hence it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears that Kings preſſing the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward act, might be ſaid to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental in promoting Faith or inward Piety, in which ſenſe it may be ſaid good Kings, as of <hi>Joſiah, They made the People to ſerve the Lord their God,</hi> 2 Chron. 34.33. But I muſt meet with an Objection which may be urged thus, granting that there was acts of Faith requir'd in acts of Sacrifice; yet thoſe being inward acts of the mind, Kings could not command or compel them.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, no earthly King can lay claim to ſuch <hi>Spiritual do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion:</hi> However Chriſtianity being not ſuch an <hi>inviſible Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:49594:23"/>but that it exerts it ſelf in ſeveral viſible acts, as confeſſion of Faith, Communion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which certainly will challenge the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates care in caſe his aid is wanted; neither will this appear as impertinent to his Office ſo long as he hath reaſon to ſuſpect that thoſe whom the Church can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reduce by her Methods, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be as good Subjects as others, when they are declar'd not to be ſo good Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Hereſie,</hi> though they do not by neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence imply <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi> not always terms convertible, yet they are ſuch as a Prince may ſuſpect, and ſeem as Vapors under the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49594:24"/>Earth, which do not always cauſe Earth-Quakes, but when they are confind to a natural Priſon, and cannot break forth, for as the one doth not always put the Earth in ſuch Convulſions, yet excite fear, ſo the other may have ſuch influence on a Princes mind, which though it cannot ſhake him (for that ſuppoſes weakneſs) yet may create a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential Caution.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>Conſideration III.</hi> Of the authority of Reaſon, as it ſtands in competition with the Church, and of <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Hereſie</hi> according to the new account of it, and whether reformation or ſeparation from Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Church, can be as ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49594:24"/>and legally juſtifi'd without an appeal to the conſtant Doctrine of the Catholick Church, as with it.</head>
               <p>TAking it for granted, that Reaſon is not the laſt Object Faith and its principles, the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments into which it is reſolv'd,</hi> as the Reaſoner phraſes it, it being not able to make a <hi>diſtinct diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very</hi> of the nature of God, and unfit Judg of rules of his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. I refer the Reader to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Diſcourſe, <hi>N. F.</hi> It there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at preſent ſeems only neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that I aſſert Eccleſiaſtical Authority with its due right, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove private Judgment of ſingle perſons, who ſo far become the Proſelytes of humane Reaſon in that ſenſe, which a late Author
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49594:25"/>aſſerted it, as they appeal to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the evidence of their own Reaſon conducted by its own natural Method, only ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the information by reading the Scriptures; and fortifying their Opinions with mere natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Arguments (without any reſpect to the conſent or autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Church. Many ſuch <hi>Proſelytes</hi> have appear'd in this late Age, and cloakt their <hi>Fox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh principles</hi> with <hi>Sheeps</hi> clothing of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Tenderneſs;</hi> yet ſtill ſeem to have a reverence for the Church and its Authority, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in late Pamphlets, which nearly lookt into, is but as an <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Compliment</hi> (if it is not a Solaeciſm to ſay ſo) for rational
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49594:25"/>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is not Authority pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly call'd, for whilſt men cauſe other mens Opinions to be tryed by the teſts of their own judgments, they cancel the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of other men, and make their own as an <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>This conſideration minds men of a Stratagem or Plot to ſubvert the authority of the Church, and eſtabliſhing their own, which is not by any way more plauſible done to an unwary Multitude than by partial citations of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, without conſidering the Coherence, Circumſtance, or Scope of the Author, which they cite. If I deſign'd to be large in this diſcourſe, I might ſhew how ſome undermine the authority of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49594:26"/>the Church, by ſiniſter and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious application of <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Story,</hi> as the Author of a late Pamphlet by the ſucceſs of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> would prejudice all Princes againſt the authority of Councils, and a partial citation of <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> (afterward to be conſider'd) but I ſhall not ſpend time in canvaſing that Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and its application, nor ſhew the weakneſs of Reaſon in its ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral particulars, only ſhall take a proſpect of Religion abus'd by ſome late partial Citations by which the Church is threatned, Holy Fathers made to ſpeak contrary to their ſcope, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion expos'd to each cavil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Adverſary.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:49594:26"/>
               <p>Thus <hi>Jerome</hi> hath been repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by ſome, an enemy to <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> as aſſerted by the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Thus the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whilſt ſome of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church urgeth it with Citations out of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which ſpeak the danger of ſeparation from the Catholick Church, they apply it to their own, as if to be <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> were all one. Thus a late Author would perſuade the Unwary, that the moſt <hi>Puritan Proteſtants,</hi> Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, do agree with Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in ſeveral points controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which they were as far from, as we can imagine they thought the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion diſtant from
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49594:27"/>the true. The Fathers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are cited againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which minds me of ſome oppoſers of the authority of the Church, who make them as a Patronage to their factious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions. Thus <hi>Lactantius</hi> is cited, the words are theſe, <hi>Lib: de Orig. Error. Cap.</hi> 8. having in the former Chapter remov'd the ſuperſtitious Rites and cuſtome of ſome ancient Fathers who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted them in <hi>Paganiſm;</hi> he infers this, <hi>Quare opportet in eâ re maximè, in qua vitae ratio verſatur ſibi quemque confidere, ſuoque ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicio ac propriis ſenſibus niti, ad inveſtigandam &amp; perpendendam veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem, quam credentem alienis erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, decipi, tanquam ipſum ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49594:27"/>expertem.</hi> Now how injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly this is affixed as a Preface, to authorize a factious Diſcourſe (as it often is) againſt the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Church, may appear from the ſcope and deſign of the Holy Father in that Chapter, <hi>viz.</hi> to oppoſe Heatheniſh Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Dreams and South ſayings, which began before Chriſtianity had footing in the word. But let it be applyed in oppoſition to the <hi>defintions</hi> and <hi>impoſitions</hi> of the Church, all that can be conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the Words in this, he condemns thoſe who in a ſtupid obſervation of the Traditions of their Fathers <hi>More pecudum ducun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> as he phraſes it, an unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable <hi>implicit Faith,</hi> which the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49594:28"/>Church of <hi>England</hi> doth not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to her Sons, but rather op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes its Aſſertors. To ſay all, this Holy Author, though an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Diſputant, and of a peircing wit, yet is ſo far from diſdaining Authority, that none more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent than he in Citations of Heathen Authors, of Poets them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to prove the weightieſt matters of Religion when he diſputed with <hi>Infidels,</hi> as he was, neceſſitated to do, as he ſays, Lib. <hi>de falſa Relig. Cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Sed omittamus ſanè teſtimonia pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetarum, ne minus idonea probatio vidcatur eſſe ab his quibus omnino non creditur.</hi> He though a Father of the Church himſelf, <hi>lib. de juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia c.</hi> 4. cites St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> arguing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49594:28"/>againſt <hi>Demetrius</hi> by Reaſon, only becauſe he was not capable of being confuted by any other Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, as appears by the account given in the ſame Chapter, <hi>Nam cum ageret contra hominem veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis ignarum, dilatis pauliſper divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis lectionibus, formare hunc a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipio tanquam rudem debuit.</hi> This gives me occaſion of conſidering what eſteem Reaſon was in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, being eſteem'd only fit to diſpoſe <hi>Infidels</hi> for Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, and to inſtruct <hi>Novices;</hi> but in this Age it is ſo exalted, that it is thought worthy of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt place of Judicature, to judg of all Controverſies, in ſo much that the <hi>Smyctimnian</hi> Divines, in their late Papers, declare it to be as
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49594:29"/>the <hi>Eye</hi> and <hi>Religion, as the Light,</hi> or <hi>the Object. Sic res ingenioſa eſt eſſe Chriſtianum,</hi> in another ſenſe than formerly, and that which the Author of <hi>Smyrk</hi> ſays of Wit, in a Jeer, may be retorted on them, for whilſt they make Reaſon an intrepreter of Scripture, we may ask them too, if their <hi>reaſon</hi> is <hi>an extraordinary gift of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To conclude this part of the Conſideration, that thoſe who interpret Scripture thus, may not boaſt themſelves <hi>Lactantius</hi> his Diſciples, but rather Proſelytes of the authority of Humane Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and by this method of making their Reaſon the only <hi>Standard</hi> to <hi>meaſure</hi> Controverſies, ſeem to appropriate the Preface us'd in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49594:29"/>General Councils (at leaſt one) and corrupting, <hi>Viſum eſt nobis &amp; Spiritui Sancto</hi> by changing the terms to every particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon who is adjuſted with equal authority, to ſay <hi>Viſum eſt mihi &amp; Spiritui Sancto,</hi> which boldneſs exceeds Poetical Licenſe, which ſeeing extraordinary acts of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, attributed it to the Gods whilſt they ſaid <hi>Sic viſum eſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This being premis'd, I paſs to the other part of this conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, <hi>viz. of Schiſm and Hereſie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the new account of it,</hi> and how Reformation is not ſo juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able without Appeals to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Doctrine of the Church.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:49594:30"/>
               <p>This Aſſertion muſt expect to find as furious a return as Water doth when caſt on hot Iron. Whilſt I affirm that <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Hereſie</hi> are two of the greateſt evils of the Church, and affirm (as I think I ſafely may) that ſome have abus'd Religion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as much by their extenua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe horrid ſins, giving a ſoft account of them ſuitable to the humour of the Libertine, as the <hi>Schiſmatick</hi> and <hi>Heretick</hi> by practice: for ſuch Theory makes way for practice whilſt they teach men that <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Hereſie</hi> are only terms of Art which the Church hath us'd to impoſe on the Chriſtian Schollars what Doctrine it pleaſes, and that 'tis
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49594:30"/>the <hi>terrors</hi> of the two <hi>Greek</hi> words (which have not ſo dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a ſignification as they ſay) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frights the poor Chriſtian like <hi>thundring and lightning</hi> to run to his Litany to <hi>pray for deliverance.</hi> This ſlight of ſubtile men will miſs its aim if it is conſider'd that the Church is not only as a <hi>Lex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icon</hi> or <hi>Dictionary,</hi> to tell the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> but hath power to inflict its Cenſures when unjuſtifiable ſeparations are attempted. This unity of the Church is as much to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd by the Paſtors of it as the <hi>being</hi> of the Church is, and that is ſo neceſſary, that I may ſay of the Catholick Church in matters of Belief, <hi>unum &amp; verum
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49594:31"/>ſunt idem,</hi> Unity and Truth are undiſtinguiſhed.</p>
               <p>Now as it is certain that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Catholick Church there is no Salvation (for it is more than a <hi>Parentheſis</hi> in our Creed) ſo is the Unity neceſſary in order to it. Wherefore all Churches who at any time endeavour'd <hi>a regular Reformation,</hi> made Appeals to ſome beſide their own private interpretation of Holy Scripture, which might be eſteem'd unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable. For if it may be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd that each man may make interpretation of the Scriptures; it is very difficult, if not impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for men (eſpecially thoſe who will have communion with none but thoſe of whom they are
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49594:31"/>aſſur'd are of the ſame opinion with them in all things) to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſo perfect charity with a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle perſon, much leſs with the whole Church. For ſuppoſe two different interpretations of ſome part of Holy Scripture, <hi>viz. This is my Body,</hi> and one takes the Body of Chriſt in the Euchariſt to be only <hi>figuratively,</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>corporally,</hi> and both agree in this, that the <hi>Conſecrated Bread</hi> is rightly call'd the <hi>Body of Chriſt,</hi> and the worthy Communicants receive it. Thus ſuppoſing that theſe words appear in different ſenſes to different perſons, how ſhall one convince the other that he is of the ſame Faith with him, if he do not expreſs it in the <hi>ſame
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49594:32"/>words</hi> and <hi>manner of interpretation,</hi> (which the Humane Reaſoner ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his account of faith eſteems not neceſſary) except he could creep into his Soul to ſee the thought and the intimate motions of the mind, without which he will not conclude any man can be declar'd a <hi>Heretick,</hi> This is an unreaſonable and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible way of diſcouraging er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in Religion, which will take away all power from the Church except it can <hi>keep Court</hi> in each mans mind, and ſee each mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it. Such private inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations are like <hi>Viſions</hi> or <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritions</hi> which appear to ſome perſons only when they are <hi>alone.</hi> Now as no man is oblig'd to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49594:32"/>the Hiſtory of ſuch <hi>Appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> no further than the Authority of the perſons obliges them to it (I ſpeak not of Holy Viſions to the Prophets) ſo no man will think himſelf bound to believe any private interpretation of a ſingle perſon, any further than he is poſſeſt with the authority of the perſon, except he could enter into his phancy, and bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the whole <hi>Scene</hi> as it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to the <hi>Viſor</hi> or <hi>Seer,</hi> which is impoſſible. Therefore it is neceſſary that there be an <hi>open profeſſion</hi> of faith by <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>pertinent</hi> words, which are as <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaments</hi> to knit together perſons in <hi>outward Communion.</hi> This minds me of the charge given by Saint
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49594:33"/>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy</hi> (2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 13.) of taking <hi>care of the form of ſound words,</hi> Whilſt he gives his character of them, that they were ſound, he omits not the <hi>form</hi> of words, which in ſome caſes may ſo alter the ſenſe, for it ſeems as neceſſary to Religion to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the true Religion from the falſe, as the Philoſophers <hi>form</hi> of diſtinguiſhing one being from another. An Inſtance in the word ſo oft repeated in late Pamphlets, is a great evidence of it for when by a Holy Father without ſuperſtition or Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of words (which Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome have made againſt the name <hi>Jeſus</hi> it ſelf, whilſt, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to be bow'd at when
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49594:33"/>nam'd) which was preſerv'd for the alteration of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, would deſtroy the Creed, at leaſt change its ſenſe, the pulling out of an <hi>Iota</hi> being as dangerous as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving a Pin, from a curious piece of Mechanical Art.</p>
               <p>This conſider'd in its conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, will further appear more reaſonable for the idle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture of the Humane Reaſoner (thoughdreſt in a <hi>Theological</hi> habit) is as much to be ſuſpected as <hi>Jeſuits</hi> Oaths, prompting men to think that equivocation in <hi>belief,</hi> as well as <hi>oaths,</hi> is to be <hi>tolerated,</hi> whilſt it is concluded that an open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the moſt obſcure Texts of Scripture is ſufficient, making
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49594:34"/>each Man's phancy a Comment on the Text, and the rule of Faith.</p>
               <p>The moſt valuable Objection which comes to my thoughts, at preſent, is this, That <hi>Jeſuites</hi> equivocate in their Oaths on deſign; but the other, if they appear ſuch, it is on neceſſity: let charity believe this and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them ſincere; yet let it be conſider'd that the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> will plead this, that he uſes this art in ſwearing, only to evade the force of ſome Obligations which the Magiſtrate would bind him to, and this he will tell us he doth that he may guard and not vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late his conſcience, and what can
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49594:34"/>the <hi>Libertine</hi> ſay more, (I ſpeak not this to patronize either, rather conclude them both worthy of cenſure) who refuſeth ſome <hi>Creeds,</hi> or at leaſt part of them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they deſcend to particulars to prevent all Equivocation. To ſay all, the only difference of the perſons practice is this, the one uſeth his art to impoſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Man, the other on God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; I ceaſe to ſtart more Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, but rather paſs to that which is granted by all who are not <hi>Enthuſiaſts, viz.</hi> that in all Diſputes there muſt be a <hi>third</hi> to appeal to. When the Heathen is diſputed with, <hi>reaſon</hi> muſt be pitcht upon as the Umpire, and the <hi>Jew</hi> appeals to the <hi>Prophets,</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:49594:35"/>and the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> to the Scriptures, interpreted by the Catholick Church, without which <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi>'s queſtion may be askt. <hi>Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtis vos? under &amp; quando veniſtis? ubi tamdiu latuiſtis? &amp;c. Tertull. de Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrip. Con. Haer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, to make each man's reaſon judg of Controverſie, is to make it both <hi>judg</hi> and <hi>party</hi> too, which may be retorted on the Church, which is a <hi>party</hi> too in deciding the Controverſie. Let this be granted, yet the reaſon is not the ſame of private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as a <hi>party,</hi> and the whole Church, and let the Libertine pitch upon any third Interpreter, wherein the Objection will not return and make it the <hi>party.</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:49594:35"/>This ſo generally obtains in moſt caſes, that a man's own mind is not paſt poſſibility of having par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, for an <hi>intereſted reaſon</hi> may aſſert that which true reaſon will deny; and a man may by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit ſo frame his mind to tell lies, and believe them himſelf. But let it be granted that the Church is a party, yet not ſuch as to be ſuſpected. It is a prodigious kind of diſtruſt to think the whole <hi>Catholick Church</hi> ſhould paſs a <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial ſentence.</hi> That Fathers will not deſign to deceive their Sons in matters of Divinty, is ſo true, that ſome have made uſe of it to prove the exiſtence of God, and ſhall the ghoſtly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers be eſteem'd ſuch Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49594:36"/>to deceive their Sons in matters of ſuch moment. To ſay all, that which a <hi>Roman</hi> Doctor aſſerted of their Church ſo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorily, may be ſaid of the whole, that it ought <hi>to give teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of it ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before I conclude this Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, I cannot but take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice that ſome who have extenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated <hi>Hereſie</hi> in its name, would alſo make it impoſſible that a <hi>Heretick</hi> ſhould be diſcover'd, becauſe to an obſtinate oppoſing the true Doctrine (in which the nature of <hi>Hereſie</hi> conſiſts) it is requir'd that the intimate mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of mens minds be ſeen. This is illuſtrated by an inſtance from Murder, to which I ſhall only
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49594:36"/>oppoſe this, that he may as well conclude it is impoſſible to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover Murther. Beſides, that ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude fails in the main part of it, for a <hi>Heretick</hi> hath oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of recanting, and muſt be an obſtinate Oppoſer of the Truth <hi>three time</hi> before he is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd ſo. Now the Murtherer is not capable of ſuch reſpite or pauſing, and opportunity of ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling his fault, or making it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be none, except he was capable of committing the act three times (as well as the <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> oppoſing truth) which cannot be except a man had <hi>three lives.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:49594:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Conſideration V.</hi> Of Creeds and Impoſitions, with ſome Reflexions on the Apoſtles and other Creeds, and of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of Creeds, how neceſſary for deciding Controverſies.</head>
               <p>ALthough there is no abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute neceſity imply'd in the nature of Religion, that there muſt be Creeds or a ſymbol of Faith, yet it may be ſafely concluded they are not ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous. It is convenient that we have an <hi>Enchiridion,</hi> and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the <hi>well being</hi> of the Church, though the ſubſtance of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49594:37"/>the Doctrine may be but as an Index to direct to its fuller Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation in particulars; and a good mean to preſerve the true Faith. Though Chriſt did not immediately draw up his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in ſuch Articles, it is paſt doubt he directed the Church to do it, and that perhaps that he might create reverence to the Paſtors of the Church, that they ſhould not be only as <hi>Library-keepers,</hi> but <hi>Authors</hi> too in that ſenſe, that a Publiſher of an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome may be call'd ſo, whilſt they compoſe the contents of Scripture in a ſhort abridgment by Divine Direction. It is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd that Chriſt did ſome things to create a Reverence to his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49594:38"/>and Apoſtles, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the charge of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of the Goſpel in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, when he himſelf could as eaſily have done it, as <hi>wrote on the ground with his finger,</hi> and ſhall not his Apoſtles Succeſſors be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed worthy to interpret theſe holy Writings. To deny them this Authority, and only allow them ſuch a mere <hi>Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial office,</hi> and that to be only underſtood as if they were only <hi>Mercuries,</hi> with a hand ſtretcht out with a <hi>Scrol for the People to read,</hi> it ſeems raſh: And to confine them only to be judg of Circumſtantials, is to mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize their Authority, and makes them but Regiſters to keep the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49594:38"/>Divine Books. 'Tis true, this is honour enough to be but <hi>Door-keepers;</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid the <hi>Jews</hi> might glory becauſe <hi>the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of God were committed unto them,</hi> which may not be reſtrained to the bare letter of the Law, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to each mans apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; but in doubtful caſes Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals were to be made to the <hi>Sanedrim,</hi> which hath no ſmall affinity with the proceedings of Councils, though ſome diſputes ſet them at further diſtance; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides. I do not remember that Chriſt taxes in general the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Doctors for Expoſition of the Law, but when they either clearly perverted the ſenſe and meaning of the Law, or plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49594:39"/>altered it by ſiniſter Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations, <hi>making the word of God of none effect.</hi> For if all Illuſtrations of the Law by <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Doctors muſt be laid aſide (though we know and avoid the fabulous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of the <hi>Thalmudiſt,</hi> many parts of the Old <hi>Teſtament</hi> would not be ſo plainly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, even thoſe which relate to the coming of Chriſt, and the manner of his Kingdom. If it is ſaid that the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Doctors often err'd, ſo their Authority ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, if not invalid, the ſame will be granted (I preſume) of Councils and Church, when their Aſſertions (if it may be ſuppoſed) are manifeſt contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions to plain Scripture. This
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49594:39"/>
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> confeſſeth, when he ſays Councils may not be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, <hi>Niſi manifeſtiſſime conſtet intollerabilem errorem, Committi lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Concil.</hi> But more of this in its proper place. In this only I ſhall take notice that the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Church hath been rendered odious to weak minds, whilſt ſome part of it (I do not mean the <hi>Catholick</hi>) run into ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams in <hi>Creeds,</hi> as ſome men in <hi>habits</hi> or <hi>cloaths;</hi> ſometimes the humour of the Age is ſuch that men affect to appear in the large ſize of Primitive Ages, others deſirous to appear as ſmall as Nature will admit, one time as Gyants, another time as Pyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. This vanity hath crept
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49594:40"/>into the Church, ſome will only own the Apoſtls Creed, others not content with thoſe which the Church hath received, but muſt make it larger by <hi>Phylacte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> of <hi>Decretals.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Roman</hi> Church will have each Article of the Creed (as <hi>Aſtronomers</hi> ſay of the Planets) each muſt have its <hi>Aſſecla</hi> or <hi>Page</hi> attend it. They will ſcarce believe that they ca ſatisfie the firſt Article of believing, in caſe it is not repreſented by Images, neither will they believe the <hi>Communion</hi> of the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> except <hi>Rome</hi> may paſs for it, and the Reſurrection, and <hi>day</hi> of <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> not to be explained without <hi>Purgatory,</hi> ſome run in another ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49594:40"/>tream, they will admire nothing ſo much as the <hi>Eunuchs Creed</hi> to be impoſed on as matters of Chriſtian belief. However they magniſie the <hi>Creed of the Apoſtles</hi> at the ſame time, decrying o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers allowed by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which gives juſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſuſpicion, that thoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perſons who own the <hi>Apoſtles Creed</hi> in <hi>words,</hi> if preſt by the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral interpretation of the whole Church, would boggle at that as much as at the <hi>Athanaſian Creed,</hi> for though they commend it (as it juſtly deſerves it) for its plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of matter, and the phraſe (ſo eſteemed by the Fathers) yet it is certain there are doubts in ſome Articles which are not
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:49594:41"/>agreed on, ſo as to be paſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute, for inſtance, the <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints, the belief on the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, and the manner of Chriſt's deſcending into Hell,</hi> not yet agreed on by all parts of the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> beſides thoſe who will have nothing in other accompts of Religion, but in Scripture phraſe, muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with other Language in this. That word <hi>Catholick</hi> hath lately been as much controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as the threadbear word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which word was ſo hard to <hi>Luther,</hi> that he went about to tranſlate it into the <hi>German</hi> Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and alter the phraſe; for which boldneſs he was juſtly charged by <hi>Tanner</hi> the <hi>Jeſuite;</hi>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:49594:41"/>for I am of <hi>nazianzens</hi> mind, not to have a word changed, for as he ſays, <hi>One drop of Poyſon may corrupt a great maſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would not have this which is ſaid of the <hi>Creed,</hi> as to be ſaid in derogation from its reverence due to it above other <hi>Creeds,</hi> which are but Comments on it, yet there are two queſtions I hope may be ſtarted without vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence done to it. How it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to be a ſum of Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals. This is well Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſome late Authors, <hi>That the Apoſtles wrote the whole ſum of what is to be believed, for if they had omitted any part of it, they might have as well omitted all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then it muſt be inquired how
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49594:42"/>far this <hi>Creed</hi> as Apoſtlical de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on the Churches teſtimony or authority; on this latter que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion the preſent Controverſie depends; therefore it muſt be conſidered what it is to be called <hi>Apoſtolical. Apoſtolical</hi> is that which is agreeable to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles practice and doctrine. So the title <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> is faſtned to ſome Churches and ſeveral per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whoſe piety had, hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance to that of the Apoſtles, but when it is given to any Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine as the rule of Faith, <hi>Ubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſemper, &amp; ab omnibus,</hi> obtains in this ſenſe the Apoſtles <hi>Creed</hi> cannot be called <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> as to all its parts, for all were not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived at the ſame time, as it is
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49594:42"/>obſerved that St. <hi>Auſtin, Origen,</hi> and <hi>Tertullian,</hi> commenting on the Creed, make no mention of the Articles <hi>of the deſcent into Hell,</hi> though 'tis confeſt Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> owns it as <hi>Catholick</hi> in other places. 'Tis true, <hi>Rufſinus</hi> an ancient Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor makes mention of that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, but ſays the <hi>Roman</hi> Church did not receive it at that time, but ſince generally received; I ſpeak not this out of any irreverence or light eſteem to the <hi>Creed,</hi> as an Author I heard of, who wrote a ſcurrilous and malicious piece a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Creed meerly in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to another opinion.</p>
               <p>That which I infer from what is ſaid, is only this; All Doctrines
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:49594:43"/>if they are not immediately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the whole Church, not raſhly to be rejected. This alſo I could infer, that ſeeing it is not certain the Apoſtles wrote it themſelves, but in ſeveral Ages it had its Ratification, at leaſt the compellation of <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> from the Church, its plain that the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Church, which makes it above other <hi>Creeds,</hi> and to be the <hi>ſum total</hi> of all that is to be believed, makes it depend on that authority of the Church, which gave it its compella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which (I hope) though borrowed from the authority of the <hi>Church,</hi> which ſince the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles time hath been abuſed, will be no greater a prejudice to
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49594:43"/>diſcerning minds, than the title of the King, though firſt derived from the Pope can minorize the honour due to him. This which is ſaid, perhaps may be retorted by an inſtance in Books of cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Scripture, by ſaying we may as well conclude that the Goſpel owes its name of Goſpel to the <hi>Church,</hi> and the Law its name of the Law, as conclude that the <hi>Creed</hi> as to its denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or being <hi>Apoſtolical,</hi> depends only upon the <hi>Church</hi> which calls it ſo.</p>
               <p>This Objection may find an Anſwer from this conſideration, that although the <hi>Church</hi> is Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial, in both <hi>holding</hi> out a Light to declare unto us that the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49594:44"/>
                  <hi>Goſpel</hi> is the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and the <hi>Law</hi> the <hi>Law,</hi> as much as it doth evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that the <hi>Creed</hi> is the <hi>Creed;</hi> yet there is this difference, the Books of the Law and Goſpel its probable had their compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation or name written by the ſame Authors that wrote them but the <hi>Creed</hi> owes its title to the reſtimony of the <hi>Church</hi> ſo far as it is call'd the <hi>Apoſtles Creed.</hi> By this limitation I hope I have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented another cavil which might conclude, I make the Doctrine of the <hi>Creed</hi> to depend on the <hi>Church,</hi> when I only ſpeak of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation as being borrowed from the <hi>Church,</hi> which compellation is the only hinge on which the preſent Controverſie turns, for
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49594:44"/>take away the name <hi>(the Apoſtles Creed)</hi> and it can be no more ſaid to be the ſum of all Religion, than other Doctrines, or <hi>Theſes</hi> generally received by the <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it is further urged that all Titles of the canonical Books bear not (without doubt) the Authors names as ſeveral <hi>Pſalms</hi> and the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> becauſe it is not certainly known who were their Authors. This may be granted, yet the caſe is not the ſame with the <hi>Creed</hi> and ſome parts of the canonical Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; for the latter it may be ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid that the <hi>Church</hi> gave no new Titles to thoſe Books, but delivered them as they found
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:49594:45"/>them waitten, or were aſſured of their Titles by infallible Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, but the ſame cannot ſo certainly be ſaid of the Apoſtles <hi>Creed.</hi> From all that is ſaid it is eaſie to obſerve how ſome men are ready to own the Authority of the <hi>Church</hi> when ſerviceable to their deſigns, and diſowns it when it thwarts private Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>It may be granted that the <hi>Apoſtles Creed</hi> is <hi>Regula fidei Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſima,</hi> as a <hi>Rule</hi> though but a foot in length, may diſcover the crookedneſs of the greateſt quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, and is uſeful in thouſands of caſes, ſo the <hi>Creed</hi> may mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and diſcover though not ſo accurately, the many Volumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:49594:45"/>errors in Religion, but not in direct terms but by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. To illuſtrate it by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, Chriſt ſums up all the Commandments in one word <hi>Love,</hi> which, <hi>modo implicito,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes againſt all Vice, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe it could not be an abridg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the whole Law, this muſt be granted, but it is raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſay that this Command alone is able to check all Vices, and conclude againſt each parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Sin. It is alſo ſaid of <hi>Manna</hi> (a fit Emblem of the <hi>Creed,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to be kept in the Ark of the Church) that eminently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains all ſavours to gratifie the Taſt and Smelling, and the <hi>Opall</hi> and <hi>Iris</hi> have a lovely commix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49594:46"/>of all colours. Now as a man who would paſs an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Judgment of a ſweet body would not appeal to <hi>Manna</hi> which hath it mixt with others, but to ſome particular object of the ſame kind, and he who would paſs judgment on Colours, <hi>Yellow,</hi> or <hi>Blue, &amp;c.</hi> will not compare them with that in the <hi>Rainbow,</hi> but ſome other Object of the ſame complexion or tincture; the ſame may be ſaid of the Articles of Faith, which are ſeverally comprehended in the <hi>Creed,</hi> yet are not to be an exact meaſure of their numerous Errors implicitly condemned by it. It hath been doubted by ſome, whether the principles of <hi>Chymiſts, Salt, Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:49594:46"/>&amp;c.</hi> are really in the Bodies, or whether they were as matter <hi>fitly prepared,</hi> and by Extraction <hi>made ſuch.</hi> I ſhall not preſume to determine any thing in this, but only apply it to the preſent caſe, by ſaying there are the <hi>Semina</hi> or <hi>Principia</hi> in the <hi>Creed</hi> but particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Articles which confute parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Errors, though they have their Foundation from it, yet their whole Superſtruction cannot be ſaid to be taken from it.</p>
               <p>It is impoſſible it ſhould be done, therefore weakneſs to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt it, for it argues as much weakneſs in thoſe men who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to aſſert the Creed the <hi>ſum of all</hi> to <hi>be believed,</hi> and to confute all Errors, as ſome when
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:49594:47"/>urged by ſome of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> to ſhew how the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were contained in the <hi>Creed,</hi> have anſwered out of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas.</hi> 2.2. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>a.</hi> 8. <hi>Eos Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulos continueri &amp; includi in Articu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo fidei quo Credimus unam ſanctam Eccleſiam, Sanctorum Communio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, Remiſſionem peccatorum,</hi> that they are contained in the Articles, where we profeſs a Belief in the <hi>Catholick Church, Communion of Saints, remiſſion of Sins.</hi> And being urged particularly to ſhew how Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm was included there, run for Sanctuary to the <hi>Athanaſian Creed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſeems to be a far fetcht and an unnatural deduction; for though it may be concluded that the Sacraments are neceſſarily
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:49594:47"/>implyed in the Remiſſion of Sins, as he gives his reaſon, <hi>Ibidem, nam per Sacramenta peccata remittuntur,</hi> it will conclude the neceſſity, but ſays nothing of the nature; wherefore that great Doctor, with all the ſubtilties of his School-companions, could never extract any thing thence of the nature of them; ſo if Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation could not find any other confutation than from thoſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, it would be to little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to diſpute againſt it.</p>
               <p>Thus one of our Church, who being urged by a Papiſt how he ſhewed in the Creed that <hi>Doctrine of the Devils forbidding Marriage,</hi> was expreſt in the <hi>Creed,</hi> anſwers that neither <hi>meats,</hi>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:49594:48"/>nor <hi>marrying</hi> of any perſons could be <hi>unlawful,</hi> becauſe a Chriſtian <hi>believes in God</hi> in his Creed <hi>to be maker of all thinks good,</hi> ſo not to be forborn, and all his Inſtitutions holy, therefore not to be abſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from by any perſons: This ſeems to me as vain an Attempt, and as far fetcht a way of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as thoſe men uſe, who will undertake to ſhew there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing New, but demonſtrate all new Philoſophy to be taken out of <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> I would not have that which is ſaid ſo underſtood, as if I did imagine there were to be <hi>Virtuoſos</hi> in Religion as well as Philoſophy, and that this Age made <hi>new diſcoveries</hi> of Doctrines as the Aſtronomers have of the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:49594:48"/>Stars, and that new Creeds in Divinity are as neceſſary as new Syſtems of the World. I am not ſo ignorant to think that No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty can commend Religion though it may Philoſophy, and that for this reaſon, the one is God's work and command, fully revealed at once after Chriſt's coming. But the product of Humane Obſervation ſuffers no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in its Reputation by being new. Neither doth Religion ſuffer, but is rather honoured whilſt new Arguments, for they muſt needs be ſo at the firſt ſpringing up of <hi>Hereſie</hi> againſt new <hi>Herſies.</hi> This therefore which is ſaid will not minorize or leſſen the eſteem of the <hi>Creed,</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:49594:49"/>which the Ancients had of it, for I cannot but own the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation which <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> gave of it, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Catech.</hi> 4.</p>
               <p>And having before ſhew'd the conciſe and compleat A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgment of it, ſays, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, compares it to Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-ſeed, more fitly and perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently than the Eunuchs is by <hi>Smyrk.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:49594:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Conſideration V.</hi> Though the Apoſtles Creed may main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Charity and Union between members of the Catholick Church, whether it can preſerve charity in a particuler Church, and in what ſenſe ſhort Profeſſions of Faith ſo much inſiſted on by late Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and commended to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament as the full matter of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Belief, and in what circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances they muſt be, and what perſons they are to whom they are ſufficient.</head>
               <p>IT may be ſaid of matters of Faith in Religion, as <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> diſtinguiſhes in Philoſophy,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:49594:50"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> principles of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and that which comes by deduction, the firſt which are as the grand Ligament or Tye, which knit the parts together, or as a foundation to ſupport a building though the root and other parts of it are demoliſhed. This is enough to denominate the <hi>Church</hi> a Church, but if there be diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement in other Doctrines which may indanger Man's Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, though not ſo imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately as thoſe in the Creed, it takes off from the beauty of it, and makes it look as in the former inſtance, like a <hi>Skeleton</hi> knit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by the Articles of one Creed, as ſinews not agreeing in any other parts, or like a <hi>frame</hi>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:49594:50"/>or <hi>caſe</hi> of a houſe without a <hi>Roof</hi> or <hi>Ornament.</hi> I ſpeak not this as uncharitable to the Catholick Church, but to ſhew how the want of Unity in all Doctrines diſguiſe it. By this Aſſertion the Catholick Church is not condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for thoſe Diviſions, which deſtroy not the <hi>Internal communion</hi> with it (though <hi>External</hi> may be wanting) but to ſhew Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty beautifies it. Wherefore thoſe who ſeparate themſelves from another Church, muſt have ſome other reaſons of their ſeparation than are in the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> otherwiſe the Reformation can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be juſtifiable, for the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church</hi> profeſſeth to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the fame Creed as a late
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:49594:51"/>Author pleads; therefore Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration not altogether founded on that. Wherfore it remains there muſt be Doctrines which juſtifie Separation from other meaſures than the Creed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This may unite in the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> but not a National or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church; for the Church cannot be minced into <hi>Individu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als</hi> without being deſtroyed, at leaſt breach of Charity, and that for this Reaſon. God under the Law and Goſpel was never ſince <hi>Adam</hi>'s Innocency worſhiped <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. Elias</hi> was miſtaken when he thought he was <hi>left alone,</hi> the only votary of the true God. I am ſenſible of an Objection which may be this; That <hi>Luther</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:49594:51"/>in the beginning of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation was the only <hi>open profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor of the Proteſtant Faith,</hi> which being granted (as it need not) muſt ſuppoſe ſome critical time of <hi>Luthers</hi> Proteſtation, in which he had no followers, which with preciſeneſs will conclude that Chriſt himſelf Head of the <hi>Church,</hi> was without any votary at his firſt birth, except his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was one; and there muſt needs be a certain time when the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were without a Church or Converts: But Religion takes notice of no ſuch Niceties; and as the <hi>Common Law</hi> takes that to be done immediately, which is done in the ſame day appointed in ſome caſes, taking no preciſe
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:49594:52"/>notice of the hours; I am ſure the Divine Law doth not diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh ſuch <hi>critical moments.</hi> But to wave theſe niceties, it was always the method of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers to make profeſſion of their Faith. Thus did the <hi>Lutherans</hi> in their <hi>Auguſtane confeſſion;</hi> for without this, Charity would not have been maintained within themſelves: So then what would the Reformation ſignifie if there may be as many, and as dangerous and different Opinions among themſelves, as there was between them and the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> their Reformation ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies little more than a Change, not for the better, but worſe; their diſſenting from the <hi>Roman
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:49594:52"/>Church</hi> might be juſtifiable, but amongſt themſelves (eſpecially in matters abſolutely neceſſary to be believed) ſuch ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion intollerable, for though the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> like <hi>Joſephs</hi> coat, may have, and be of divers co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours and parts, but particular, muſt be like Chriſt <hi>ſeamleſs</hi> coat, or to ſpeak the Apoſtles Langu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, <hi>like minded,</hi> and ſpeak the ſame thing.</p>
               <p>Now this Unity of the Church is not better preſerved by any means than by Appeals to ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral interpretations of places of Scripture (which are ambiguous) by the Councils, Fathers, and Paſtors in ſeveral Ages. Thus the Champions of the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:49594:53"/>always owned that Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity as the beſt means to win Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and the beſt ſubſidy to ſupport it. The neceſſity of this ſeems to be implyed in the Apoſtles Advice to ſubmiſſion to Paſtors, and the Paſtors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to give an accompt for the Peoples Souls. I know theſe words may occaſion a volumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Diſpute.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall take them in their plaine acceptation, and only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the Reader to obſerve that in caſe this ſubmiſſion to Paſtors, is only to circumſtances confin'd, as ſome will have them, and yet Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors give an accompt, it is like a Man who is inveſted with the power of a <hi>Tutor,</hi> yet only to
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:49594:53"/>take care of his <hi>Pupils Cloaths.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This muſt be reſtrained to pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which have a doubtful ſenſe, and the definitions or interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſuch as the words will bear, for I am not ſo bold to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with ſome of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that it hath a power to command a Doctrine, which hath no <hi>probable foundation in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> (as Doctor <hi>Stapleton</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes that ſome things are to be believed, and the Church pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound them as matters of Faith, <hi>Etiamſi nullo Scripturarum evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denti aut probabilis teſtimonio comfir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metur,</hi> though he at the ſame time concludes the Church in its definitions is, <hi>Suo modo Divina.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:49594:54"/>
               <p>It fares with the Church in its deſiring matters of Faith, as it doth in proſpects, for though <hi>Teleſcopes</hi> and Perſpections help the Sight, yet there muſt be a rude diſcovery of the Object by the naked Eye, thus the <hi>Milky way</hi> is diſcerned without the help of a Glaſs to be a <hi>bright tract</hi> of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, by the <hi>Teleſcope</hi> which diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers that troop of ſmall Stars from which it borrows its Luſtre. The caſe is the ſame between Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and the Church (I mean obſcure places of it) the one gives an ambiguous <hi>Twilight pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect,</hi> the other ſhews it more <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus I have endeavoured to commend the Churches Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:49594:54"/>as a neceſſary Supplement to the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> or in order to maintain Charity amongſt mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of particular Churches (for I do not deſign in this Paper to anſwer all Objections that the former diſcourſe may be lyable to.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I now paſs to the other branch of the Conſideration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In what ſenſe ſhort profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Faith ſo much inſiſted on by the Reformers, and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Parliament, can be ſaid to be the full matter of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith, and in what circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances they muſt be in to whom they are ſufficient. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:49594:55"/>ſuch curtilizing Creeds do not again introduce that implicit Faith, which this Church com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaineth of whilſt under <hi>Papal</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions.</p>
               <p>For further demonſtration of the neceſſity of the extent of the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> by Explanation it ſeems convenient that I ſuggeſt that uſual diſtinction of Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals in reſpect of their mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the perſons to whom they are offered as objects of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief. To the firſt 'tis enough that I ſay one Aſſertion may be a Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental though not primarily ſo, which in reſpect of another, is but as a corrollary or branch of it, as it is eaſie to inſtance in the <hi>Apoſtles Creed.</hi> To the ſecond it
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:49594:55"/>will be ſufficient to ſay that all Doctrines are not preſſed on all perſons with the ſame neceſſity or upon peril of Salvation, which will plainly appear from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the Requiſites ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to make ſuch neceſſity. The firſt of which is this, <hi>viz.</hi> A conviction of the mind, that what is propoſed as matter of Faith, muſt be commended to Man by God, for there is no <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane dictator</hi> can command any matter of Belief to Man merely as Humane. Thus the Apoſtles themſelves doubted of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, or at leaſt were not ſufficiently convinced of it till matter of fact convinced them of their <hi>Maſters</hi> being <hi>God</hi> as well as <hi>Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:49594:56"/>
               <p>Another Requiſite, is, that there muſt be a ſufficient propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal of matters of Faith, otherwiſe it is inſignificant to a man, for what is Revelation to him to whom it is propoſed, for matter of Faith is like Objects which are in their own nature viſible, yet the Eye doth not always actually ſee them, neither can it in ſome ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes till more conveniently ſitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or impediments removed. Thus <hi>Apollos</hi> ignorance and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect Creed, excuſable till he was more fully inſtructed of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> for the Doctrines of which he doubted before, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though as the Sun they always ſhin'd, yet as the one cannot be ſeen till above the <hi>Horizon,</hi>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:49594:56"/>though it is obvious to other eyes, ſo the ot her not aſſented unto till ſufficiently explained. If this ſeem not oppoſite, take an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance more Divine. As none could ſee the City of <hi>Samaria</hi> (though it was naturally as viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to other perſons) but the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, ſo none diſcern <hi>Divine Truth</hi> till Grace makes the diſcovery.</p>
               <p>The laſt is a diſpoſition of mens minds fit to receive ſuch <hi>Divine impreſſions;</hi> thus Mad men and Fooles are not to be expected <hi>Converts to Religion, who are Aliens and Strangers to their own Reaſon;</hi> and in this ſenſe that applauded concluſion <hi>of the vanity of holding a Candle, and attempt to make one ſee whom nature deſigned for darkneſs,</hi>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:49594:57"/>and to this head the citations out of St. <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> (afterward to be conſider'd) and others muſt be reduced leaving ſuch <hi>Idiots,</hi> to the cenſure of <hi>God himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This being promis'd, I hope I may more fairly conclude againſt thoſe concluſions which factious heads have drawn from thence, for all that can be inferred from ſuch charitable cenſures, is only the modeſt cenſure of the <hi>Church,</hi> whilſt it reſpects God's Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute; ſo that thoſe perſons who have ſo formally made addreſs to Authority for tolleration of ſhort Creeds, muſt plead their cauſe in the ſame circumſtances they thus indulg'd were, which is impoſſible, except they can An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidate
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:49594:57"/>time and be as the Apoſtles were then, or men now, who are uncapable of <hi>Divine Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> wherefore I may ask thoſe men this Queſtion, whether they ſpeak for themſelves, as of the Clergy, or for other perſons, if for others (which I preſume they will be ready to own as officious Advocates, they bring in the Doctrine of the <hi>Author of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Reaſon,</hi> the Reaſoner ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing it to a ſufficient aſſent to Chriſtian Doctrine if Scripture is commented on by a private in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention.</p>
               <p>This part of the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (if I deſign to be tedious, would lead me to examination of the ſeveral cavils againſt
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:49594:58"/>Councils as to the quality of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and to anſwer an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> who ſaith he never ſaw a happy event of a Council; which words concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to all I have met with, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns not Councils, but rather is a complaint of the want of free and general Councils, as is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to any who conſiders that Author's drift and deſign. But I paſs from this and other curious cavils by conſidering that ſuch niceties in Religion are like que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions about the Stars, whoſe Nature and Influence we are ſenſible of, and can probably demonſtrate their Natures, but not in ſuch a way as can anſwer queſtions that a roving brain can
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:49594:58"/>ſtart, and can ſhew greater pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability that they are ſuch, than the extravagant invention can, they are not, but I ſhall not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue this Digreſſion rather return to the former caſe.</p>
               <p>This being granted, it muſt be conſidered that theſe perſons with their ſlender ſtock of Faith, are admitted into the Church as men into an Hoſpital, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity rather than Reaſon, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes them in a ſafe ſtate of Salvation. Now is it not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable to propoſe that as a Model or meaſure of Faith to all which is only indulged to Mad men and Fools, or at leaſt men of weak capacities, and that on no better ground than that tender
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:49594:59"/>one of extenſive charity, ſuitable to which are the accounts of the Church given by the Ancients whilſt it is thus deſcribed, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a certain num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Elect in which may be babes in Chriſt, fooliſh as well as wiſe, and compared to the Ark, when there was a univerſal recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Creatures, which were clean.</p>
               <p>If theſe Zealous Petitioners ſpeak for themſelves, then that ſmall meaſure of Faith and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row capacity, will be an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt them in the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their own party. But if it is alleadged that <hi>Rahab</hi> had but a ſmall meaſure of Faith, and
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:49594:59"/>yet Sainted by St. <hi>Paul</hi> (at leaſt) in the catalogue of eminent Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers) and the <hi>Centurion</hi> with his ſlender knowledg of Chriſt had no leſs commendation from Chriſt himſelf. Let it be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that this is not applicable to Paſtors of the Church. What a medley and ill favoured being of a Church would that be in which a <hi>Rahab</hi> or <hi>Convert-Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot,</hi> 2 <hi>Centurion</hi> or <hi>Souldier,</hi> ſhould aſſume a <hi>Clerical</hi> power. The Records of late times, the odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous face of the Church (if it may deſerve that compellation of the Church) prevents me in ſaying more.</p>
               <p>This which is premiſed will make way for this concluſion.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:49594:60"/>That the exacting of neceſſary Oaths, Subſcription, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and other means of Comformity are no otherwiſe an intrenching on Liberty than the exigency of Chriſtian Society requires, and the Savage may as well complain of Policy, which reduced them from their wilde and natural ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancy, as the Libertine of a Teſt or tryal of his conſcience ſo far as it concerns the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate.</p>
               <p>This perhaps may appear too Magiſterially ſaid, if I do not give the Reader the plea for Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and ſuggeſt this as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.</p>
               <p>Before theſe conſiderations are cloſed, I cannot but add
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:49594:60"/>this, That ſome who diſdain all Auxiliaries and Aid from the authority of the Fathers and Councils, ſeem to preſs them into ſervice of the Church, when they find any clauſe that may aid them in their wild and arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Model of Eccleſiaſtical Government.</p>
               <p>Thus I find Saint <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> among the Ancients, cited as an enemy to the Method which ſeems to force Religion, and <hi>Grotius</hi> amongſt the latter, which practice ſeems like that of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted Politicians, who will let Statutes lye as an old Armory (fit for ſervice) but not to be uſed till occaſion furbiſhes them and gives the ruſty Iron an edge.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:49594:61"/>That this may not ſeem <hi>gratis dictum.</hi> Let the former Author be conſidered, whoſe Paternal Indulgence and Inſtruction to the Prieſts ſpeaks favourably of weak Chriſtians, his words are theſe, <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Sacerdot.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Grotius</hi> his favourable words extend only to the not propagating of Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion by force, not contradicting the uſe of the Civil Power in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement or well compoſing a Church already planted.</p>
               <p>This I preſume will be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath endeavoured to reduce re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractory
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:49594:61"/>men, by all imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable means, and when that takes not effect the Civil pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er begg'd to aſſiſt them, which contradicts the ſenſe of the Holy Father, who only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns to ſhew that Clerical power proceeds not in the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of a Temporal Prince; and another citation of <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian,</hi> is to this purpoſe, whilſt he ſays they are to be tenderly handled, <hi>Qui bono animo. Errant;</hi> or as a late Author ſays, <hi>Ill Believers.</hi> For ſpeaking of the <hi>Arrians,</hi> he makes this Plea for them, <hi>Non Odio ſed affectu dei ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norare &amp; ſe Dominum &amp; amare cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:49594:62"/>
               <p>This plea cannot be made in this Age, for it may well be ſuppoſed that the <hi>Arrians</hi> (of whom he ſpeaks) had not the ſame opportunity of being confirmed in Religion, the Queſtion debated being only confirmed by one Council, but that in diſpute now by many. So that Refractory Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons of factious Zealots may be askt <hi>Tertullian's</hi> Queſtion, <hi>Interea perperam Evangelizabatur tot millia millium perperam tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta, tot opera fidei perperam ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrata, tot virtutes, tot Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſmata perperam operata, tot Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotia perperam functa, tot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nique Martyria perperam Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:49594:62"/>
               <p>To ſay all, time which blots out other characters, makes Religion more legible, and Martyrs blood as a Rubrick to each clauſe of the <hi>Divine Law</hi> ſo plain, that Man may rnn the courſe of his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral life, and read his ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to Heaven.</p>
               <p>But if this unhappy Age gives inſtances of thoſe which cannot, and deſire to be tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated in their ignorance, their only plea muſt be their weakneſs, which in matters of Religion can have no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way of proceſs than <hi>Sub forma pauperis</hi> (if I may bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the Lawyers term) as
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:49594:63"/>men of weak apprehenſion; and the defect of their <hi>narrow Faith</hi> muſt be ſupplyed or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved from Heaven, not Earth, from God (who alone knows how to rate the <hi>poverty</hi> of <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> according to its <hi>true value</hi>) not Man. And ſuch a Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration (if its term may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed as it concerns God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) muſt have its compleat Ratification, not only from the <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Churches Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency,</hi> but God's higheſt and laſt Judicature.</p>
               <p>To conclude all, it ſeems a more pertinent way for ſuch to addreſs themſelves to the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine</hi> rather than <hi>humane Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and endeavour that God
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:49594:63"/>may <hi>incline</hi> his ear to their <hi>Prayers,</hi> and <hi>increaſe</hi> their <hi>Faith</hi> rather than attempt to <hi>ſupple</hi> and <hi>bend</hi> the Magiſtrate to complyance by <hi>fervent petitions.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:49594:64"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49594:64"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>REad St. <hi>Malo</hi> Page 5. r. launching out into p. 8. r. Arguments are like p. 10. r. all error p. 19. r. the deſign of Chriſt in this place p. 21. animate or inanimate p. 23. r. before I paſs p. 24. r. except ſome of which that were miraculous p. 32. becauſe latter Kings p. 33. minds me p. 41. footing in the World p. 45. r. three times p. 63. Articles of the Creed ſuch p. 70. r. threadbare word p. 72. r. defining p. 98. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectives ibid. and diſown p. 80. r. expreſt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd p. 85. for God under Law and Goſpel never ſince, r. God never ſince <hi>Adams</hi> Innocency was only worſhiped but by one Votary, p. 92. r. <hi>probabili</hi> p. 97. r. complain'd p. 100. p. 112. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
